Binliu Zhang

github.com/cool4zbl linkedin.com/in/binliu-zhang

Software engineer with 7 years of experience developing large-scale, high-performance applications and systems, especially in location-based services and A/B testing, serving over 100 million users by technology.

A self-motivated life-long learner, keen to explore best architectural practices to serve teams and customers.

Skills

- Programming Languages: JavaScript/TypeScript, Go, Python, Java, SQL
- Technologies: PostgreSQL/PostGIS, Redis, Kafka, ElasticSearch, AWS/Azure, CI/CD, Kubernetes, React/Vuejs, Node.js

Work Experience

Senior Software Engineer

Grab

Feb 2021 – Present

Geo - Collection team

Beijing, China

- Built and delivered features for Jarvis, a unified crowdsourced task management platform based on an event-driven
 architecture, and leveraged PostgreSQL for reliable datastore and ElasticSearch for high-performance data querying,
 collecting over 400k map data through 300k Jarvis tasks.
- Led and shipped the microservice of street-view image collection and the portal, and reduced task processing time from weeks to hours by delivering automated quality checks using Go and Redis distributed lock.
- Simplified coordinates by 70% per Jarvis polygon task by proposing and applying the "Doug-Peuker" algorithm, reducing the rendering time in Web and App and resulting in a better user experience.
- Stretched CI/CD and Azure Pipeline, reduced build time by 50% during CD, and utilized Datadog as monitoring, improving development efficiency and quality.
- Onboarded and trained 7 new hires on Grab's tech stack and development best practices.

Senior Fullstack Engineer

Alibaba

Jan 2018 - Jul 2020

AntGroup - Data Platform team

Beijing, China

- Redesigned and revamped the front-end of Darwin, a one-stop A/B testing platform, increased the company's business conversion rate by about 2% and saved over \$10M in marketing costs through over 5,000 A/B experiments per year.
- Led the implementation of an end-to-end UI A/B testing solution from 0 to 1, programmed a pluggable UI system, seamlessly integrated Darwin into 20+ internal platforms using TypeScript and React, and reduced the experiment creation time from days to minutes, empowering business growth via A/B testing.
- Defined, designed, and developed runtime SDKs of experiments that shielded various device differences, encapsulated a unified, easy-to-use API, and served over 1,000 experiments in 10+ scenarios, impacting more than 15 million daily active users.

FrontEnd Engineer

Douban

Jul 2015 - Sep 2017

User Product team

Beijing, China

- Constructed Web and Hybrid pages for Douban's 4 product lines using JavaScript and Python, serving nearly 100 million users.
- Revamped the login/registration UI of the site using React and made it compatible with multiple versions and ends.

Education

B.Sc. Electronic Engineering, <u>University of Electronic Science and Technology of China</u>

2011 - 2015

Volunteering

Mentor Feb 2022 - Apr 2022

• Mentored 9 junior STEM women to help them grow by sharing my experiences and thoughts, encouraging them, addressing their career confusion, and promoting gender equality in the STEM industry.